Good afternoon, quick sound check.
下午好，快速试音。
Can people hear me?
大家能听到我说话吗？
Yes.
是的。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Okay, so I guess today you know so far,
好的，我想今天到目前为止，
it's the last lecture of 6.S081 this semester.
这是本学期的最后一节 6.S081 的课。
And, we don't really have a formal topic,
我们并没有一个正式的话题，
there's a Q&A lecture,
这是一个问答课程，
so feel free to ask questions about anything,
所以你可以随便问任何问题，
this is I guess last,
我想这是最后一次，
your last chance at least this semester for this class.
至少是你们这学期最后一次上这门课了。
By default, my plan was
默认情况下，我的计划是
to go over a couple topics based on the questions over email,
根据电子邮件上的问题复习几个主题，
then I was going to talk a little bit about network lab, the solutions.
然后我要稍微讨论一下网络实验的解决方案。
If possible, also a little bit of time about the mmap lab,
如果可能的话，再花一点时间介绍一下 mmap 实验，
again talking about those solutions.
再次谈论这些解决方案。
And then there were a lot of questions about the following classes
然后有很多关于后续课程的问题，
and in fact I think I'll cover that first.
事实上，我会先讲到这一点。
But before diving in any of these three topics,
但是在深入到这三个主题中的一个之前，
let me remind you there's a subject evaluation outgoing ongoing,
让我提醒你，有一个科目评估正在进行中，
and we as staff of 6.S081,
而我们作为 6.S081 的工作人员，
we appreciate you give your feedback on 6.S081.
我们感谢你对 6.S081 的反馈。
And hopefully it's positive,
希望它是积极的，
you know we get a chance to teach again next year.
我们明年有机会再次授课。
And maybe this is also a good time
也许这也是一个很好的时机，
to you know actually thank you for attending today's lecture,
谢谢你们参加今天的课程，
even though there's not a sort of very formal program,
即使没有非常正式的计划，
I also appreciate the fact that with the staff
我也感谢工作人员，
and generally appreciate the fact that you know you're being very engaged,
我很感激你们非常忙碌，
and in particular the paper that not directly to the labs,
尤其论文不是直接对应实验，
you know it's clear that many of you dove into the papers
很明显，你们中的许多人都深入论文中，
and try to really understand them,
试图真正理解它们，
and ask great great question of over email.
在电子邮件上问一些很棒的问题。
So, we very much appreciate the engagement.
所以，我们非常感谢你们的努力。
Any questions, before I go with each set of topics?
在我讲每个主题之前，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let me start with the question that probably came up most in email,
好的，让我从电子邮件中出现最多的问题开始，
what next.
接下来是什么。
There's a quite a number of classes that systems oriented focused,
有很多课程是面向系统的，
and I'm sure I missed a number of classes,
我肯定我错过了一些课，
that I should have listed here,
我应该在这里列出的，
you know immediately straightly related to operating systems,
它与操作系统直接相关，
you know clearly you know if you have taken 6.033 yet,
当然，如果你学过 6.033 ，
it's a great class to take,
这是一门很棒的课程，
particularly we read or learn how to read papers.
尤其是我们阅读或学习如何阅读论文。
6.828 which the originally only OS class we offered,
6.828 是我们最初提供的唯一操作系统课程，
this year or second year we're,
今年或者第二年，
this year first year of offering both,
今年是提供这两门课的第一年，
so 6.S081 is undergrad OS
所以， 6.S081 是本科生操作系统，
and 6.828 as the grad level OS class.
6.828 作为研究生的操作系统课程。
And you know basically 6.828 issues
6.828 假设，
you've taken 6.S081 or undergrad OS
你已经选了 6.S081 或本科生操作系统，
and you know goes off in new projects and building interesting OS artifacts,
在新的项目和构建有趣的操作系统工件，
and reading more papers from the literature
从文献中阅读更多的论文，
and more of the modern research literature.
以及更多的现代研究文献。
Then maybe you are more you know,
然后也许你更，
the OS sort of you know there's a lot of interfacing with the hardware,
操作系统有很多与硬件的接口，
would have been more of the hardware side of systems,
有更多的系统的硬件方面，
you know the computer architecture class 6.823,
计算机架构课程 6.823 ，
which I believe is offered to the coming Spring
我相信会在即将到来的春天提供，
and of course there's 6.111,
当然还有 6.111 ，
you know sort of the building something hardware devices.
是构建硬件设备的东西。
On the sort of performance sides, in the compiler sides,
在性能方面，在编译器方面，
6.172, 6.035 for a good places,
6.172 6.035 是个好地方，
a number of you are taking 6.172 in parallel with 6.S081,
你们中的一些人同时选修了 6.172 ，
so but if you have taken for example the compiled class 6.035
如果你选了编译课程 6.035
or dynamic compiler class,
或动态编译器课程，
both of them are also great classes.
它们两个也都是很棒的课程。
System is a broad topic,
系统是一个宽泛的话题，
so like there's networking
所以，这里有网络，
and there's a whole branch of classes
以及一大批课程，
whole [] of classes around networking,
围绕网络的整个课程，
and a whole stream of class around databases,
以及围绕数据库的整个课程，
which are all good and important,
这些都是好的和重要的，
and aspects that you've seen in 6.S081
你在 6.S081 中看到的方面
will show up in much more prominent ways in those classes.
将在这些课程中以更重要的方式出现。
For example, networking clears a great topic of 6.829,
比如，网络是一个很棒的话题 6.829 ，
and so you'll see a lot more about networking there,
你会在那里看到更多关于网络的内容，
than you've seen in 6.S081,
比起你已经在 6.S081 中看到的，
6.830 you know we talked about file systems,
6.830 ，我们讨论过文件系统，
you know clearly another important classes of storage systems,
是另一种重要的存储系统，
and probably in some ways more important for many applications, databases,
可能在一些方面对许多应用程序更重要，数据库，
and so you get 6.830 a great topic class
所以你有 6.830 这个很棒的课程
to learn a lot more about databases.
来学习更多关于数据库的知识。
In terms of like classes,
这些课程，
that are sort of you know sometimes called whatever the PDOS classes,
有时叫做 PDOS 课程，
there's a number of them,
这里有很多课程，
6.824 distributed systems class will be offering that,
6.824 分布式系统课程将开设，
coming semester Spring semester,
在下学期春季学期，
and section of the number of the staff involved this semester in 6.S081
本学期在 6.S081 涉及的教职员工，
will be involved in 6.824.
将参与 6.824 。
There's 6.858 which is a computer security class,
有 6.858 是计算机安全课程，
we won't be offering in that coming this Spring,
今年春天我们不会提供，
but we hope to offer it the next academic year.
但是我们希望在下一学年提供。
And there's 6.826 which are principles of computer system,
有 6.826 是计算机系统原理，
so a number of people ask about verification and system software,
有很多人问起验证和系统软件，
this is the class you take,
这就是你要学的课程，
if you are interested in that topic.
如果你对那个主题感兴趣。
More broadly speaking,
更广泛地说，
a lot of people wondering what is actually going on in research,
很多人想知道研究要怎么继续，
if you're interested,
如果你感兴趣，
you know almost all the papers in the systems literature are publicly available,
几乎所有系统文献的论文都是公开的，
even the ones of the recent conferences,
甚至最近的会议，
for example the OSDI conference happened a couple weeks ago,
比如， OSDI 会议在几周前举行，
and you can just look at them
你可以看着它们，
and see what kind of topics are covered
看看有哪些主题，
and read the papers that you find it interesting,
看看你觉得有趣的论文，
all the talks are published,
所有的讨论都发表了，
one of advantages of, you know, conference,
会议的优势之一，
that all these conference are virtual,
所有这些会议都是虚拟的，
and so all the conferences are recorded,
所以所有的会议都被记录下来了，
and you can just watch them and see what's going on.
你可以查看它们，看看发生了什么。
If you interested in the sort of two parts,
如果你对这两部分感兴趣，
there's the research part,
这里有研究的部分，
then of course there's what's going on in practice.
当然还有实践中正在进行的事情。
And you know if you're interested in
如果你有兴趣
keeping track of what's happening with Linux
跟踪 Linux 正在发生的事情，
and how that's how it's evolving,
以及它是如何发展的，
lwn.net actually publish a very regular page and a very interesting articles
lwn.net 发布了常规的页面和非常有趣的文章，
about like big changes or topics that are around the Linux kernel.
关于围绕 Linux 内核的重大变化或话题。
Finally you know, if you're just excited about like doing the labs,
最后，如果你对做实验感到兴奋，
you know just keep keep hacking,
只需要继续 hack 就行了，
I think you can easily to cook up projects
我认为你可以很容易地创造出项目，
are either by doing extension of labs
要么通过扩展实验，
or just trying things out on your own,
或者试一试你自己的事情，
it's a great way to really learn and appreciate how things work.
这是学习和查看事物运作方式的一种很好的方式。
You probably got a good sense of that during the labs,
你在实验里可能对此有很好的感觉，
we're sort of big fans of learning by doing
我们是边做边学的铁杆粉丝，
and a lot that you can do on your own.
还有很多你自己可以做的事。
Any questions about what next after 6.S081?
关于 6.S081 之后的下一步，还有什么问题吗？
Okay?
好的？
Well, let's talk about the net lab,
好的，我们来谈谈网络实验，
it was due I guess yesterday.
我想昨天就截止了。
And so as a couple things,
有几件事，
maybe I'll start dive in slowly,
我会慢慢开始深入，
I start a little bit at the top,
我从最高层开始，
and let me talk a little bit in generic terms about the lab.
让我用普通术语来讨论一下实验。
There's a couple things right,
这里有几件事情，
first, I want to talk a little bit about just sort of structural things,
首先，我想稍微谈谈一些结构性的东西，
that sort of influence the design of the lab
这会影响实验的设计，
or you know the coding of the lab.
或者实验的编码。
And there are four different things in aspects,
这里有四种不同方面的东西，
one of these I just want to talk a little bit about hardware,
其中一个我想谈谈硬件，
you know, this is one of the labs where we,
这是实验中的一个，
there's a lot of interaction between software and hardware,
软件和硬件之间有很多交互，
in fact the hardware determines for a great part
事实上，硬件在很大程度上决定了
like how the the structure of software.
软件的结构。
Then a little bit about software structure,
然后稍微介绍一下软件结构，
and just sort of back to this general topic,
回到这个一般性的话题上来，
that we covered in a sort of somewhere in the middle of the term
我们在学期中期的某个地方谈到了，
about you know the organization of drivers
关于驱动的组织，
relative to the rest of the operating system kernel.
相对于操作系统内核的其他部分。
Then talk a little bit more specific about hardware structures,
然后更多讨论一下关于硬件结构，
you know the rings, and you know the descriptors,
rings ，以及描述符，
are the two primary sort of hardware structures,
是硬件结构的两个主要部分，
that the driver deals with or it must deal with.
驱动程序必须处理的。
And then I'll talk to talk about the code and particularly the solutions,
然后我会谈到代码，特别是解决方案，
and focusing on a little bit about the role of mbufs,
关注一下 mbufs 的作用，
you know locking a lot of questions over email,
还有通过电子邮件的锁的很多问题，
about why not to lock in receive lock, receive in the receive function,
关于为什么不对接收函数加锁，
why the loop in the receive handler,
为什么在接收处理程序中的循环，
and you know what exactly you know the flags meaning the command,
以及命令的标志代表什么，
command field of the structure of the descriptor.
描述符结构的命令字段。
and so we'll get to those issues
我们将查看这些问题，
as we as we look at the top as we look at the code.
同时查看代码。
Just before drive in,
在开始之前，
it may be worthwhile,
可能是值得的，
so reminding ourselves here,
在这里提醒我们自己，
what the challenges are,
挑战是什么，
although they're probably fresh in your head,
尽管它们可能还在你的脑海中记忆犹新，
like from a high level
从高级别来看，
and one of the sort of core [] challenges,
一个核心[]挑战，
that you have to deal with in this lab.
你必须在实验中解决的。
If you'll jump in to any ones,
你可以在任何时候跳进来，
that I might have missed and you struggled with.
如果我可能错过的和你[挣扎]过的（问题）。
So, first of all you know there's the hardware specification,
首先，是硬件规格，
you know it's a PDF,
这是一份 PDF 文件，
is a pretty serious document,
是一份很严肃的文件，
and this network card E1000,
这个网卡 E1000 ，
even though it's a reasonable simple network card,
尽管它是一个非常简单的网卡，
is still a very sophisticated piece of hardware,
仍然是一个非常复杂的硬件，
that offers a lot of different features and ways you can program,
它提供了许多不同的功能和编程方式，
and you're just getting on top of actually
你需要掌握，
what you know the card does and how do you program it,
卡的功能，以及你是如何对它进行编程，
you know just internalizing all that is difficult and poses a challenge.
它的内部是困难的，也是一个挑战。
Second, I think you know major challenges, the concurrency side of things,
第二，我想你知道主要的挑战是事情的并发性，
and there's sort of two parts the concurrency that makes this lab challenging,
有两个部分的并发性使这个实验具有挑战性，
one is just the concurrency between the hardware and software,
一个就是硬件和软件之间的并发性，
like the network card is just doing things,
比如网卡在做一些事情，
like sending package, receiving packets at the same time,
比如同时发送数据包，接收数据包，
you know the OS kernel is running and the driver is running,
操作系统内核在运行，驱动程序也在运行，
and so there has to be some coordination plan between the hardware and software,
所以在硬件和软件之间必须有一些协调计划，
you know to actually make sure that everything works out,
确保每件事都能顺利解决，
and a large part of the driver is you know dealing with that coordination.
驱动的很大一部分都在处理这种协调问题。
There's also the software software coordination,
还有软件与软件的协调，
the driver multiple threads, or multiple kernel threads
驱动程序多个线程或多个内核线程
might be ending around handler run inside of the driver,
可能在驱动程序内部运行的处理程序周围，
and we've got to make sure that,
我们要确保，
they don't step on each other's toes, nothing else happens,
它们不会互相践踏或类似的事情发生，
and this comes a lot to like you know locking topic.
这在锁主题中会有很多。
Even the, even this driver,
即使这个驱动，
thinks a reasonable straightforward, in terms of the concurrency for software concurrency,
就软件并发性而言，想法是非常直接的，
but nevertheless you know something that requires attention and a little bit of thinking.
但是尽管如此，你还是需要注意和思考一些事情。
And finally I guess that was probably on the top of your list or many of your list,
最后，我想可能在你的列表中，
just debugging this is a little bit hard,
就是调试有点困难，
a little bit something more challenging of pure software debugging,
更具挑战性的纯软件调试，
because you can't set breakpoints inside of the network card,
因为你不能在网卡内部设置断点，
you know you're in program the registers,
你在对寄存器编程，
and then this would give the card a kick and say like please do your work,
然后它会让网卡做好工作，
and then if the card doesn't do anything
如果网卡什么也不做，
or you don't see your packet coming out on the other side,
或者你看不到你的数据包从另一端出来，
you know in the log of the packet rates,
在数据包率的记录中，
then you basically have to scratch your head
那你就很挠头了，
and start thinking about what you might have gone wrong
并开始思考可能出了什么问题，
or what you might have missed in the hardware specification,
或者你可能在硬件规范中漏掉了什么，
and you have to circle back and forth,
你必须来回绕圈，
and there's no sort of easy way,
而且没有一种简单的方法，
you just cannot single step you know through the network card.
你不能单步调试网卡。
Does that make sense in terms of challenges,
就挑战而言，这能理解吗，
you know there's that line up with your own experience
这与你自己的经历是一致的，
or I missing some of the,
或者我错过了一些，
missing one of the core challenges that you dealt with.
错过了你处理的核心挑战。
Okay, well, yeah.
好的，好的。
Let's talk to the,
让我们来谈谈，
let's start with the hardware side of things,
让我们从硬件方面开始，
and the reason I want to start there,
我想从那里开始的原因是，
because you know, it's so easy to keep or lose track of the fact,
因为，很容易记住或忘记这样一个事实，
that you're actually dealing with hardware here,
你是在和硬件打交道，
you know even through you know sort of virtualized where it is emulated by QEMU,
即使通过某种虚拟化，使用 QEMU 对其进行模拟，
and you're just running it on your, on Athena or your laptop,
你只是在你的 Athena 或笔记本电脑上运行它，
the actual thing that's implemented by QEMU is hardware.
QEMU 实现的实际是硬件。
So it's usually gonna remind you again,
所以再次提醒你，
you've seen this picture before,
你之前看过这张图片，
you know the way to think about it is that,
你知道思考这件事的方式是，
you know QEMU emulate a complete board of devices and processor.
QEMU 模拟了一个完整的设备和处理器电路板。
And.
还有。
And so we all know, I'm talk a little bit before about,
所以，我们都知道，我在之前说过的，
the processor actually these are like almost like a small piece of the whole board,
处理器就是整个电路板的一小块，
you know the thing that sits under the fan here,
是在风扇的下面的东西，
but then there's a range of devices,
但是还有一系列设备，
you know that are connected or can be connected to this board,
这些设备都连接到或可以连接到这块板上，
and then interact you know with the code running on the processor,
然后与运行在处理器的代码进行交互，
you know here use this particular lab,
在这里使用这个特殊的实验，
what is really interesting sort of,
真正有趣的是，
it is actually Ethernet jack,
它是以太网插孔，
where you can plug Ethernet cable,
在那里你可以插入以太网电缆，
and then the other is actually the thing that the network card you know sends its package over.
然后另一个网卡把它的数据包送过来。
You know, QEMU doesn't emulate exactly this board,
QEMU 并不完全模仿这块板，
so things like are slightly differently,
所以事情略有不同，
but again you know at least conceptually,
但是，至少在概念上，
this is like the picture, you should have in your in your head, right,
这个图片，你应该把它放在你的脑海里，
and so when there's a process writing registers,
当有进程写入寄存器时，
you know of the device driver that costs some stuff to happen,
设备驱动程序会花费一些东西才能发生，
that actually in the end some packages comes out of this cable,
最终一些数据包从这根电缆里出来，
that's connected to Ethernet connector.
它连接到以太网接口。
You know in a slightly more,
你知道的更多的，
you know in a slightly more in a schematic diagram,
在示意图中更多的，
you know this is the same picture basically in here,
这里的图片是一样的，
you know we're seeing here is our processor,
我们在这里看到的是处理器，
board that has four cores on it,
电路板上面有四个核心，
it has l1 and l2 cache,
它有 L1 和 L2 缓存，
and then there's like a link you know go to memory,
然后有一个到内存的连接，
so here's a memory, and the RAM random access memory,
这是一个内存， RAM 随机存取寄存器，
and as we'll see in a second,
正如我们稍后将看到的，
you know that play is actually big role.
它是一个重要的角色。
And here like intersection to link you know to the,
这里[交叉]连接到，
for here actually it's linked to the gigabit Ethernet controller,
在这里连接到千兆以太网控制器，
you know, just a little bit messy,
有点混乱，
you know sort of think about the this level of detail what exactly is going on.
思考这个级别的细节是怎么回事。
And so for the rest of lecture,
所以对于课程的剩余部分来说，
here a little bit more simpler picture,
这里的图片稍微简单一点，
and the picture guys really you should you're in your head
图片在你的脑海里，
and you probably developed while doing lab is as follows.
你可能是在做实验的时候开发的，如下所示。
Basically have are basically four processors or cores,
基本上有四个处理器或者核心，
here's are RISC-V,
这里是 RISC-V ，
and then there's RISC-V of cores
然后这里是 RISC-V 核心，
and execute instructions you know you're writing,
并执行你编写的指令，
and you can just think about them,
你可以想想看，
they're sort of all connected to your bus,
它们都连接到总线上，
and then there's a little bit of simplification,
然后有一个小的简化，
but like it makes it easier to explain things.
这会让你更容易解释事情。
And so on the bus, you know there's the random access memory,
在总线上，那里有随机存取存储器，
where all the data you know the kernel actually uses store,
其中有内核使用的所有数据存储，
the kernel [] that itself stores,
内核本身的存储，
you know look at there's a great amount of detail in the beginning of the semester.
我们在学期开始的时候看到很多细节。
And then this you know for this particular lab,
然后对于这个实验，
the thing that's interesting is that on the bus,
有趣的是，在总线上，
is actually the network card you know E1000, that E1000.
是网卡 E1000 。
And you know the RAM is generally more connected to the RISC-V processor
RAM 通常连接到 RISC-V 处理器上，
directly with some private bus,
更多地是通过一些专用总线，
and network devices tend to be on a slower type of bus,
而网络设备则是较慢类型的总线上，
in particular bus that in the lab,
尤其是实验中的总线，
you know there's a PCIe PCIe bus,
这里有一条 PCIe 总线，
that actually connects the processor part you know with the network part.
连接处理器部分和网络部分。
You know to get the network to do something,
为了让网络做点事情，
the network card has controller inside of it,
网卡内部有控制器，
and you know these controller has registers,
这些控制器有寄存器，
and you can,
而且你可以，
one of the cool aspects of you know these registers,
这些寄存器的一个很酷的方面是，
they are called memory mapped IO registers,
它们被称为内存映射 IO 寄存器，
and so you could just write them
所以你可以写入它们，
with whatever a star you know, 0x and whatever the value is
使用 *0x 或者别的什么值，
you know for in the physical memory space,
对于在物理内存空间中，
what the value is for that particular register,
那个寄存器的值是多少，
you know, like we might have our head, our tail registers.
比如我们可能有头和尾寄存器。
And you know we can, the driver can write those
你知道我们可以，驱动程序可以写入它们，
by executing load or store instruction
通过执行加载或存储指令，
you know to the address you know of corresponds you know in the physical address space
到对应物理地址空间这个地址，
to the location of that register.
到寄存器的位置。
And the hardware will ensure when we do load or store,
硬件将确保当我们加载或存储时，
you know that that store will either go you know go to the,
那个存储要么去，
if it is one of the control register, will go to the control registers,
如果它是控制寄存器，则转到控制寄存器，
if the go one address is in RAM, will go to the RAM.
如果是在 RAM 中的地址，则会进入 RAM 中。
So you can just manipulate the program network card
所以，你可以对网卡编程，
by loading, reading and writing these control registers,
通过加载、读取和写入这些控制寄存器，
and basically bits in these control registers have special meaning as you have seen.
正如你看到的，这些控制寄存器中的位具有特殊意义。
Now, for this particular card
现在，对于这个网卡，
you know network needs to send packets across the network,
网卡需要通过网络发送数据包，
and you know it needs to get the packet somewhere.
而且它需要从某个地方获取数据包。
And so, the packets actually live,
所以，数据包实际上是在，
you know are allocated as we'll see in a second
就像我们稍后会看到的那样，
you know just live somewhere in memory,
分配在内存中的某个地方，
and and what we do is,
我们所做的就是，
in fact, in addition to these packets,
实际上，除了这些数据包之外，
you know there's sort of two ring structures that also live in memory.
还有两个环形结构也在内存中。
And, and we can you know program,
而且，我们可以编程，
and we can tell the card,
我们可以告诉网卡，
you know the card also knows where these ring structures are,
网卡也知道这些环形结构在哪里，
you know it has address where to you know tx ring is,
它有 tx 环的地址，
you know it has an address where to rx ring is,
它有 rx 环的地址，
and you know the hardware card looks at those addresses
硬件网卡会查看这些地址
to actually see which packets need to be sent,
来查看需要发送哪些数据包，
so here we might have a queue of packets that need to be transmitted
所以，在这里，我们可能有一个需要传输的数据包队列，
or a queue packets that need to be received.
或者一个需要接收的数据包队列。
And, you know the E1000 you know DMAs,
还有，你知道 E1000 ， DMA ，
you know for example like you know they're going to work on the first packet to sent,
比如它们会在第一个数据包发送时工作，
it will DMA basically you know those packets data associated with the the packets,
DMA 是那些与数据包关联的分组数据，
you know straight from RAM to the network,
直接从 RAM 到网络，
without actually having the processor involved at all,
在完全不涉及处理器的情况下，
what is called DMA, direct memory access.
这就是所谓的 DMA ，即直接存储器存取。
Okay?
好的？
Does this makes sense in terms of a more abstract picture
这个概述图片能理解吗，
for the organization of the RISC-V RAM and E1000.
对于 RISC-V RAM 和 E1000 的组织来说。
Any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
So, one thing in talking about hardware, software concurrency,
所以，在谈论硬件、软件并发性时，
clearly you know the E1000 and you know the processor
显然，你知道 E1000 和处理器
are both manipulating these transmission and reception queues or rings.
同时操纵这些发送和接收队列或环。
And so, there has to be some protocol
所以，这里有某种协议，
sort of given taken give and take protocol,
给出和获取协议，
where you know at some point,
在某些情况下，
particular parts of the ring are operated, are owned or operated by the network card,
环的部分是由网卡拥有和操作的，
and there are parts that are maybe under control of the software or the OS kernel.
有些部分可能在软件或操作系统内核的控制下。
And you'll see in a second how that is arranged,
稍后，你会看到这是如何安排的，
but you know we got a little bit careful,
但是我们需要小心，
again, that the card doesn't trip over or trip over the operating system
网卡不会[绊倒]操作系统，
or the other way around.
反之亦然。
A quick question,
一个简单的问题，
so is there a separate transmit ring and and receive ring in the RAM
RAM 中是否有单独的发送环和接收环，
and then, also in the E1000 or E1000 driver.
然后，也在 E1000 驱动程序中。
Yeah, well, the one way,
是的，有一种方法，
okay, so there's two things going on,
好的，有两件事发生，
and we look at the code in a second,
我们稍后看一下代码，
the the the transmission ring and receive ring basically lived in RAM,
传输环和接收环驻留在 RAM 中，
and both the E1000 and the RISC-V manipulates the ring that actually stored in RAM,
E1000 和 RISC-V 都可以操作存储在 RAM 中的环，
and those are the rings that you saw in the hardware documentation.
这些就是你在硬件文档中看到的环。
It happens to be the case,
它是这种情况，
that xv6 also has a driver maintains a sort of a ring of mbufs,
xv6 也有一个驱动程序维护 mbuf 环，
separately of the transmit ring and rx ring,
与发送环和 rx 环分开，
like there's something like tx mbufs.
比如有类似 tx mbuf 的东西。
And that's you know that is the data structure
这是数据结构，
only the operating system really knows about,
只有操作系统才了解的，
the network card doesn't really know about it,
网卡并不知道这个，
and network card only knows about the the tx ring and rx ring,
网卡只知道 tx 环和 rx 环，
because those are the values that were programmed into the registers,
因为这些是编程到寄存器中的值，
saying like here's where you can find,
比如，这里你可以找到，
here's the address where you can find the transmit ring,
这里你可以找到传送环的地址，
here's the address where you can find the receive ring.
这里你可以找到接收环的地址。
Okay, that makes sense.
好的，理解了。
That makes sense?
这个可以理解吗?
Okay, so that's sort of the hardware picture,
好的，这就是硬件图片，
in a more schematic version.
一个更简明的版本。
Let's talk a little bit about the software structure,
让我们稍微谈谈软件结构，
there's a big confusing actually in this in this lab.
在这个实验有一个很大的令人困惑的地方。
So software structure.
所以，软件结构。
So, let's just draw you know the thing,
所以，让我们画出
that we most care about of course you know the driver,
我们最关心的事情，驱动程序，
so here's our driver, the e1000 driver.
这是我们的驱动程序， E1000 驱动程序。
And it basically has only two functions,
它只有两个函数，
it has a transmit function and it has a receive function.
它有一个 transmit 函数和一个 recv 函数。
And the receive function runs in response to interrupts,
并且 recv 函数响应中断，
so an interrupt happens,
所以中断发生了，
then you know xv6 you will use the usual interrupt mechanism,
然后 xv6 将使用通常的中断机制，
you know a trap happen,
一个 trap 发生，
trap look you know to see if there's an interrupt from the network card,
trap 查看网卡有没有中断，
if there's an interrupt,
如果出现中断，
the network card will call the receive function.
网卡将调用 recv 函数。
And as you remember,
正如你们所记得的，
we used to have one of the previous lectures about device drivers,
我们曾经有一节关于设备驱动程序的课程，
you know it's often helpful to think of the device drivers were split in two parts,
将设备驱动程序分成两部分通常是有帮助的，
you know the bottom half which runs in the context of of interrupt handler,
下半部分运行在中断处理程序的上下文中，
typically [name] for those in the top half,
通常命名为上半部分，
which generally runs in the context of you know kernel process or like a user level process,
它通常运行在内核进程或用户级进程的上下文中，
so for example if you think about things that sit on top of here,
比如，如果你想一下位于上面的东西，
there's the network stack code,
这里是网络栈代码，
that actually implements you know IP UDP and etc, sit above this.
实现 IP UDP 等，位于这里。
And then you know there is,
然后你知道，
you know, our usual you know sort of line,
我们通常的线，
you know kernel space below, user space up,
内核空间在下面，用户空间在上面，
and you know this is [] OS view of the world,
这是操作系统的世界角度，
where user space not particularly that big or important,
用户空间不是特别大或特别重要，
and you know for example are whatever nettest in the user level program
比如用户级程序的 nettest ，
runs in user space and it makes system calls,
运行在用户空间并进行系统调用，
system calls go to the network stack,
系统调用进入网络栈，
for example like if you knew calls the write system call with a file descriptor,
比如，使用文件描述符调用 write 系统调用，
the kernel knows you know for that file descriptor, if you do write,
内核知道，如果你写入那个文件描述符，
then you know the write should go to the network stack,
那么写入会发送到网络栈，
the network stack builds up the packets,
网络栈建立数据包，
and then it calls transmit.
然后它调用 transmit 。
And then transmit whatever manipulates the transmission queue,
然后 transmit 操作发送队列，
that the tx queue or ring,
或 tx 队列或环，
and you know that actually gets packets you know of network,
它会从网络中收到数据包，
at some point a response might go back come back,
在某种程度上，响应可能会返回，
you know that will generate an interrupt,
那会引起中断，
and then the recv function will run
然后 recv 函数将运行
and inspect you know the receive ring, right.
并检查接收环。
So there's a couple things that you know wanna,
所以有几样东西，
I want to point out you know in terms of concurrency.
我想指出的是在并发性方面。
And so, first of all, like the interrupt handler,
所以，首先，中断处理器，
basically can run at any instant in time, right,
可以运行在任何时间，
you know you might be user space,
可能是用户空间，
and if interrupt comes in
如果出现中断，
you know the interrupt mechanism will cause
中断机制将导致
you know the current user program to switch to the kernel mode,
当前用户程序切换到内核模式，
you know the trap functionality of code,
你知道 trap 的功能代码，
we've seen before it runs,
我们之前已经看到过，
and it will all received.
它将会全部收到。
So we might be in the middle of some user process,
我们可能正处于某个用户进程中，
in boom, we get an interrupt
我们得到一个中断，
and suddenly we're in the recv function.
突然我们就进入了 recv 函数。
And even in the kernel,
即使在内核中，
like if we're not holding locks,
如果我们没有持有锁，
you know locks turn interrupts off,
锁会关闭中断，
but we're not holding locks,
但我们没有持有锁，
we could get an interrupt,
我们可能会被中断，
and the kernel may change the program counter basically to the interrupt handler
内核会将程序计数器改变为中断处理程序，
and run the recv function.
并运行 recv 函数。
So this code sort of runs you know the things that in the bottom half,
所以这段代码是运行在下半部分的东西，
you know can basically run instantly almost anytime.
基本上任何时候都可以立刻运行。
In the code, in the top half,
在上半部分的代码，
it really operates on behalf of a user level processes or kernel threads,
它在用户级进程或内核线程运行，
that actually make calls into the top half.
调用上半部分（的线程）。
You know easily could have been the case,
很容易的情况可能是，
in fact this is the case even in nettest,
事实上，即使在 nettest 中，
we might actually have nettest for a whole bunch of processes,
我们可能会对很多进程进行 nettest ，
that we have actually many instances, one of the tests,
我们有很多实例，其中一个测试，
we have many instances of nettest running,
我们有很多 nettest 运行的实例，
and they all jump into the network stack,
并且它们都跳到网络栈中，
and they all you know then called transmit, right.
它们都调用 transmit 。
So that is the case,
所以情况就是这样，
so we're looking at this from the perspective concurrency,
所以我们从并发性的角度来看待这个问题，
multiple senders can be actually in the context,
多个发送者可以位于上下文中，
it can be in the top half,
它可以位于上半部分，
and so it's pretty clear,
所以很明显，
you know we need some locking scheme or discipline
我们需要一些锁方案或准则，
to at least make sure that different senders don't trip over each other.
至少确保不同的发送者不会被对方绊倒。
Then on the bottom half,
然后在下半部分，
there's only one interrupt handler, correct,
只有一个中断处理程序，
there's never in the case that the receive is going to be called by multiple,
永远不会有多个接收器同时运行，
there's multiple receivers running at the same time in parallel on different cores,
多个接收器并行同时运行在不同的核心上，
you know the the interrupt handler when an interrupt happens,
当中断发生时的中断处理程序，
the process is alert it,
进程会发出告警，
and if future interrupts happen,
如果将来发生中断，
they're actually blocked until the current interrupt actually dealt with,
它们会被阻塞，直到当前中断被处理为止，
and so in fact, when the recv function runs,
所以事实上，当 recv 函数运行时，
there's actually only one interrupt handler running,
只有一个中断处理程序在运行。
at the time that calls for recv.
在调用 recv 时。
And so there's no real immediately concurrency in recv itself,
所以，在 recv 本身中并不存在真正的并发，
although of course the transmit you know threads can run concurrently with the interrupt handler,
当然 transmit 线程可以与中断处理程序并发运行，
for example, we might have one core running an interrupt handler,
比如，我们可能有一个核心运行中断处理程序，
may have another core actually is about to transmit.
可能有另一个核心运行 transmit 。
This, any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
It's sort of important to have, to understand.
它是一件很重要的需要理解的事情。
It's a bit of review but it's important too.
这是一点复习，但也很重要。
Okay, so.
好的，那么。
I guess, I have a general question,
我想，我有一个一般性的问题，
how do we know,
我们怎么知道，
what is supposed to be classified as a bottom half and the top half?
什么应该被归类为下半部分和上半部分？
So, yeah, I think the way to think about it is that,
是的，我认为考虑这件事的方式是，
anything that runs in the context of an interrupt handler,
在中断处理程序的上下文中运行的任何东西，
that's the bottom half,
都是下半部分，
and in this case is basically just receive.
在这种情况下，就是接收。
And anything that runs in the context of regular process or thread kernel thread,
而在常规进程或内核线程的上下文中运行的任何东西，
you know that's the top half.
就是上半部分。
Okay, so if you look at this picture a little bit more,
好的，如果你再仔细看一下这张图片，
since where,
从哪里，
actually let me have a high level statement here,
让我在这里做一个高级别的声明，
a lot of people ask you know why no locking receive,
很多人问为什么没有对接收加锁，
and where is lock needed.
以及哪里需要加锁。
And so the first glance,
所以第一眼看上去，
it might not be necessary to lock if necessary, correct,
它可能不需要加锁，
because there's only one instance of receive running,
因为只有一个正在运行的接收实例，
so there's not multiple instances of receive running at the same time,
没有同时运行多个接收实例，
and so these receives,
所以这些接收，
since there's only one receive,
因为只有一个接收，
it doesn't share data structures with any other receive,
所以它不与任何其他接收共享数据结构，
because there's only one of them, right.
因为只有一个。
Now, of course it could be the case,
现在，当然可以是这种情况，
that the receiver and the transmitter shared data structures,
接收者和发送者共享数据结构，
but as we see in a second that actually is not the case,
但是我们随后会看到，不是这种情况，
basically the transmission part of the driver is completely separate from
驱动程序的发送部分完全独立于
the reception part of the driver, receiving packets.
驱动程序的接收部分，接收数据包。
And so as a result, receive doesn't really, doesn't need actually locks,
所以，接收并不需要真正加锁，
you know it's really not sharing data structures with any other concurrent activity.
它并不与任何其他并发活动共享数据结构。
Weird part is that you know some of you found out,
奇怪的是，你们中的一些人发现，
if you do use a lock, you actually get a panic.
如果你使用了锁，会引发 panic 。
And so let me say a little bit about that,
所以让我简单地说一下，
because the reason that panic happens is,
因为 panic 发生的原因是，
a little bit because there's,
有一点是因为，
this the software structure actually in in xv6 kernel slightly,
在 xv6 内核中的软件结构
slightly more complicated than you might think,
比你想象的要稍微复杂一些，
and the reason is that
原因是，
basically the receive interrupt handler just quite a bit of work,
接收中断处理程序做了相当多的工作，
or can do quite a bit of work,
或者可以做相当多的工作，
so let me talk a little bit about it.
所以让我稍微谈谈这件事。
In the particular case that actually does quite a bit of work,
在特定的情况下，它做了相当多的工作，
for example ARP requests,
比如， ARP 请求，
ARP is one of those packet types that Robert talked about a little while ago,
ARP 是 Robert 之前谈到的数据包类型之一，
but basically what happens like an interrupt comes in,
但发生的事情就是中断进来，
so an ARP request for discovery the ethernet addresses where an IP address you know comes in,
ARP 请求用来使用 IP 地址发现以太网地址，
you know that will call you know eth1000_recv,
它会调用 eth1000_recv ，
and you know that will call whatever net_rx,
它会调用 net_rx ，
so that will go call into the network stack on the previous pictures,
这样就会调用前面图片上的网络栈，
so that receives calls into this code over here,
让接收可以调用进入这里的代码，
net receive you know calls,
net receive 调用，
oops net receive calls net_rx_arp,
糟糕， net receive 调用 net_rx_arp ，
and it and you know it looks you know there's an ARP packet,
而且它查看，这里有一个 ARP 数据包，
and basically sends back the ethernet address for this particular for xv6,
并且发回 xv6 的以太网地址，
and then the way it does that of course you know to send the packet,
然后它做的是发送数据包，
it will call you know, e1000_transmit right,
它会调用 e1000_transmit ，
and you know we know that will actually need to acquire a lock,
我们知道，这需要获取一把锁，
well, you did that you know whatever there's eth1000_lock.
你使用 eth1000_lock 来完成它。
The reason that actually has to go on a lock is,
这里必须加锁的原因是，
because there might be multiple senders
因为可能有多个发送者，
and you know the senders should not trip over over, trip over each other.
发送者不应该被对方[绊倒]。
So that's sort of the picture,
所以这是一张图，
so what we're basically in terms of this previous picture,
所以我们就前一张图片而言，
what we're seeing here is that,
我们在这里看到的是，
the bottom half may end up call the code in the top half,
下半部分可能最终会调用上半部分中的代码，
and come back into the driver through the top half.
然后从上半部分回到驱动程序。
And a number of you know you run into trouble with that,
你在这里遇到了麻烦，
because you know the you know it's not 100% clear,
因为不是百分之百清楚，
that you didn't need a locks in the receiving part,
你不需要在接收部分加锁，
and so quite a number of you run into this particular bug,
所以你们中很多人遇到了这种特殊的 bug ，
where you're actually required the you know eth1000_lock in receive.
你在接收中获取了 eth1000_lock 。
And that worked all fine correctly,
这一切都很正常，
except once in a while you get a panic,
只是偶尔你会得到 panic ，
why do you get the panic,
为什么你会得到 panic ，
hopefully with this picture, that's pretty clear about.
希望这张图片能让你看得很清楚。
I mean, isn't it going to be the same lock,
我是说，这不是同一把锁吗，
because that the e1000_transmit is going to try to acquire eth1000_lock.
因为 e1000_transmit 将尝试获取 e1000_lock 。
Yeah exactly, correct,
是的，没错，
so eth1000 here at this point now owns the lock, holds it,
所以在这一点上， eth1000 拥有这把锁，
calls net_rx, calls net_rx_arp, e1000_transmit,
调用 net_rx ，调用 net_rx_arp ，e1000_transmit ，
then calls acquire again,
然后再次调用获取，
and as you might remember from previous labs,
你们可能还记得以前的实验，
if require it's called it's already held,
如果叫它调用获取已经持有的，
that's a deadlock right,
这会是个死锁，
and so xv6 kernel panics.
所以 xv6 内核出现了 panic 。
Question, let's let's assume we had a slightly different implementation of locks,
问题，假设我们的锁实现略有不同，
such as those functions are not occur,
比如那些函数没有发生，
like it would such,
比如，它将，
let's assume like if I wanted to acquire a lock already held,
假设，如果我想获得已经持有的锁，
nothing happened.
而且什么都没有发生。
Yeah so, these are these are called recursive locks,
是的，这就是所谓的递归锁，
or reentrant locks is another way the name for them.
或者另一种名称是可重入锁。
And so if you have a recursive locks, reentrant locks,
所以如果你有一个递归锁，可重入锁，
then you know you could freely do this
然后你可以自由地做这件事，
and it would be no problem.
它不会有问题。
And I think one of you over email mentioned to me,
我想你们中的一位在电子邮件中提到，
that actually the implemented recursive locks to actually deal with this particular problem.
实现递归锁才能真正解决这个问题。
And so they did required to lock in the eth1000_recv function,
所以他们在 eth1000_recv 函数中获取锁，
and you know after the panic,
在 panic 之后，
basically fixed acquire release in the xv6
修复在 xv6 中的获取和释放，
[direction] support recursive locks.
通过支持递归锁。
And that would be a solution.
这也是一个解决方案。
The simple solution, it's a fine solution,
一个简单的解决方案，
the solution that we intended and the staff solution as is
我们计划的和工作人员的解决方案是，
basically just doesn't require locks in receive at all,
根本不需要在接收中获取锁，
because it actually turned out not to be necessary.
因为这是没有必要的。
Sorry, can you say again,
对不起，你能再说一遍吗，
why there couldn't be two threads in receive?
为什么在接收中不能有两个线程？
There's only one thread in receive, the interrupt handler runs,
在接收中只有一个线程，即运行中断处理程序，
there's only one receive function ever running at the time on any core,
在任何内核上，一次只有一个接收函数在运行，
that actually calls into the top half of the, the top half of the operating system
它会调用操作系统的上半部分，
and that calles back out into the bottom half,
然后调用回到下半部分，
sorry not in the bottom, that calls back into e1000_transmit
抱歉，不在下半部分，调用回到 e1000_transmit ，
and transmit definitely needs to acquire a lock,
而 transmit 肯定需要获取锁，
so even receive, eth1000_recv, while holding the lock calls e1000_transmit,
所以，即使 eth1000_recv 在持有锁的同时调用 e1000_transmit ，
which tries to acquire the same lock that the interrupt handler already holds,
e1000_transmit 尝试获取中断处理程序已经持有的相同的锁，
if you have, if you locked in receive handler.
如果你在接收处理程序中持有锁。
I see, so so it is the case,
我明白了，所以是这样的，
like one interrupt can go off
比如一次中断会发生，
and then while it's still running,
然后，当它还在运行时，
another interrupt could go off as well, is.
另一个中断可能也会发生。
No, no, the picture, maybe go back to this picture,
不，不是，那张图片，也许可以回到这张图片上，
so interrupt happens, that calls the receive function,
所以中断发生了，它调用接收函数，
there's only one receive function running,
这里只有一个接收函数运行，
that receive function calls you know rx net receive,
接收函数调用 rx net receive ，
that calls rx net_rx_arp,
它调用 net_rx_arp ，
and that arp function calls transmit,
那个 arp 函数调用 transmit ，
and if you were using the same lock in transmit and receive,
如果你在发送和接收中使用相同的锁，
you know you would get a deadlock.
你会陷入死锁。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
That's sort of, yeah, okay,
有点像是，好的，
and so basically the two solutions to this,
所以基本上有两种解决方案，
one is to use recursive locks,
一种是使用递归锁，
other solution was no locks in receive,
另一种解决方案是不在接收中使用锁，
or you know have two locks.
或者使用两把锁。
All three of them are totally reasonable solutions.
这三个都是完全合理的解决方案。
Any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Would there be a reason to have a lock around receive at all?
会不会有理由在接收周围加锁呢？
No, in this particular case,
不，在这种情况下，
there's no reason to have a lock at all.
根本没有理由加锁。
What would be, could we think of a situation
我们能想出这样一种情况，
where you would want a receive lock,
如果你想要一个接收锁，
would be like if you had two network cards or something.
比如你有两块网卡之类的。
Yeah, or if you like if you remember in the UART code,
是的，如果你还记得 UART 代码，
okay, so may a common reason why you might want to have a locking shared is,
好的，你可能想要锁的一个常见原因是，
because the bottom half and the top half shared data structures.
因为下半部分和上半部分共享了数据结构。
So, for example the receive and transmit might manipulate the same shared data structures,
所以，比如，接收和发送可能操作相同的共享数据结构，
at that point you need you need a lock,
在这一点上，你需要一把锁，
and so for example you remember from your console driver,
比如，你记得在控制台驱动程序中，
they shared a queue,
它们共享一个队列，
and so receive handler needed to get queue,
所以接收处理程序需要获得队列，
need to get the lock to actually get access to that queue.
需要获取锁才能访问那个队列。
Does that answer your question?
这回答了你的问题吗？
Yeah, thanks.
是的，谢谢。
And so this brings me up with a second sort of point I wanted to make.
这就引出了我想提出的第二点。
That the let me actually draw a new picture,
让我画一幅新图，
because it gets a little crowded.
因为它有点拥挤。
We think about this bottom half again, and the top half.
我们再次考虑下半部分和上半部分。
So here's the bottom,
所以，这是下半部分，
a little bit abstract, but you know it may be helpful.
有点抽象，但是它可能会有帮助。
In much typically in much software, driver software,
在多数驱动程序软件中，
the bottom half basically doesn't really call into the top half at all.
下半部分基本上不会真正进入上半部分。
So, for example if you go back and you look at the console code,
所以，如果你返回并查看控制台代码，
this sequence of the sequence cannot happen there,
这个序列不可能在那里发生，
and the reason doesn't happen is,
而没有发生的原因是，
because the bottom half typically does very little work,
因为下半部分通常做的工作很少，
the only thing it does maybe you grab the packet,
它唯一能做的就是抓到包，
stick the packet in the queue.
把包放在队列里。
And then, at some point later,
然后，在后来的某个时候，
you know the the top half, you know there's a separate thread in the top half,
在上半部分有一个单独的线程，
that basically looks at that queue and then grabs packets out of the queue,
它查看那个队列，然后从队列中抓取数据包，
and then keeps on doing whatever needs to be done.
然后继续做任何需要做的事。
Now, for simplicity a in this simplicity and reduce the amount of code,
现在，在这一简单性并减少的代码里，
that is not the structure that these particular driver follows,
这不是这些特殊的驱动程序遵循的结构，
this driver once in a while may actually call up in,
这个驱动可能偶尔会调用，
call up actually sometimes this structure is followed by the driver,
有时驱动遵循这个结构，
but once in awhile, it can actually go into the top half
但偶尔，它可以进入上半部分
and come back out into the bottom half.
然后回到下半部分。
Any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
Okay, so that's sort of I guess software concurrency
好的，我想这是某种程度上的软件并发性，
and we'll come back to a little more later,
稍后我们会回到更多的话题，
if we look at the code in a bit more detail,
如果我们更详细地看一下代码，
talk a little bit about the rings.
稍微谈一下关于环的事。
And so basically the way you think about it,
所以基本上就像你想的那样，
you know there ring,
这里有环，
there's two rings and one for receiving and one for sending,
有两个环，一个用于接收，一个用于发送，
you know tx rx both lives in RAM.
tx tx 都在 RAM 里。
And you know they're manipulated by code running on the RISC-V cores
它们是由运行在 RISC-V 核心上的代码操作的，
and by you know the network card itself.
以及网卡本身。
So there has to be some protocol
所以有某种协议，
between the network card and the RISC-V of course,
在网卡和 RISC-V 之间，
about who gets to look at what,
关于谁可以查看什么，
and so the way this is a very common organization in hardware devices,
所以，这是硬件设备中非常常见的组织方式，
the way that typically is done,
通常的做法是，
there's sort of, look at the transmit queue,
在某种程度上，看看传输队列，
there's basically a queue of some fixed size structures descriptors,
有一些固定大小的结构描述符的队列，
as we'll looking in a second,
我们马上就会看到，
these are the descriptors.
这些是描述符。
And the organization or the coordination that is actually
组织或协调，
that's happening between the driver and network card is
发生在驱动程序和网卡之间的是，
the consumer producer coordination.
消费者与生产者的协调。
Basically, one way to think about it,
可以用一种方式来考虑，
you know there is if this is the transmit queue,
如果这是传输队列，
you know there's maybe there's a head pointer,
也许这里有个头指针，
there's a tail pointer,
这里有一个尾指针，
and you know this the tail pointer is controlled by the software,
尾指针是由软件控制的，
and so the software looks at the tail pointer,
所以软件会查看尾指针，
and it wants to send, send another packet,
它想发送另一个数据包，
sticks it you know in a the ring at the location of tail plus one,
把它放在在环里尾指针加 1 的位置，
and then moves up tail pointer in that direction.
然后把尾指针向那个方向移动。
And the head pointer is usually controlled by the hardware.
而头指针通常由硬件控制。
So tail by software, head by hardware
所以尾由软件控制，头由硬件控制，
and basically the you know the hardware basically looks at the head,
基本上，硬件查看头指针，
and this is the first packet that is going to be sent,
这里第一个数据包是要发送的，
you know there's a little bit of information in the descriptor,
在描述符里有一些信息，
or enough information that descriptor for the network card to look at,
或者描述符有网卡要查看的足够多的信息，
and say like oh this is the bytes that I need to move on to the move on to the cable.
比如，这是我要移动到电缆的字节。
And once it's done, it moves the head pointer in that direction,
一旦完成，它就会将头指针朝那个方向移动，
once it's consumed you know one of the packets out of the transmission queue.
一旦它使用传输队列中的一个数据包。
And one way to think about it is that,
考虑这个问题的一种方式是，
all the descriptors between here, between the tail,
所以在这里和尾之间的所有描述符，
and so all the things that are actually being filled in,
所以填入的所有东西，
like the tail moved up maybe to here.
比如尾指针移动到了这里。
You know all the packets,
所以数据包，
that are all the descriptor entries that are actually filled in,
作为填充的所有描述符条目，
the way you think about them is,
你考虑它们的方法是，
they are owned by the hardware owned by the network card.
它们属于网卡硬件。
The network card is allowed to read them, do things with them,
网卡允许读取它们，用它们做事情，
but the software and the software is not allowed to do anything with that,
但是软件不允许对它们做任何事情，
like if the software would be scribbling over these descriptors,
如果软件在这些描述符上[乱涂乱画]，
while they really sort of owned by the hardware by network card,
它们在某种程度上是由网卡拥有的，
that would change the data that the network card sees,
这将改变网卡看到的数据，
and that would be pretty undesirable.
这将是非常不想看到的。
And so, the protocol basically is
所以，协议基本上是，
that like once you know the software moves the tail pointer one up,
就像软件将尾指针向上移动了一个，
then you know that point you have just moved into the network queue in the transmission queue
然后你刚刚移动的点会到网络传输队列中，
is now owned by the hardware,
现在归硬件所有，
and it will stick in,
它会在，
you know it will be owned by the hardware until it has to be sent,
它将归硬件所有，直到它必须被发送出去，
and basically until the head pointer moves past you know that particular structure.
直到头指针移动过那个特定的结构。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Good, for transmission, basically it's the same story,
很好，对于传输来说，也是一样的故事，
you know there's a there's a head pointer,
有一个头指针，
that basically that's controlled by the hardware,
它是由硬件控制的，
and there's a tail pointer,
这里有一个尾指针，
that is controlled by, there is the software pointer,
它是由软件控制的，
and basically the packets in between
在两者之间的数据包
are are packets are actually have been received by the hardware,
是硬件已接收到的数据包，
and and you know by expecting the tail pointer,
通过期待尾指针，
and the software can see if there's actually a new packet,
软件可以查看是否真的有新的数据包，
you know that is ready to be consumed,
它已经准备好可以使用了，
and if that ready to be consumed,
如果它已准备好可以使用，
the hardware will indicate that by saying that DD bit in the status field.
硬件将通过在状态字段中声明 DD 位来表示。
And so when the DD bit is set,
因此当设置 DD 位时，
hardware software are good,
硬件和软件都是好的，
you know these packets, you know the hardware is done with it,
这些数据包，硬件已经完成了，
and so it can take it out and move the tail pointer one up.
所以可以把它拿出来，把尾指针向上移动一个。
And so there's sort of this give and take between driver and our hardware
所以，在驱动程序和硬件之间存在某种的收发，
to actually coordinate they don't trip over each other.
为了协调它们不会被对方[绊倒]。
Any questions about the rings?
关于环，有什么问题吗？
Is this like,
这是不是，
is this a universal way to kind of implement,
这是不是一种普遍的实现方式，
like user or any kind of communication between two things that have shared memory?
比如用户或具有共享内存的两个东西之间的通信？
Yeah, it's a pretty certainly also in software, you see this,
是的，这当然是在软件中，
but many hardware devices play this sort of trick,
但是很多硬件设备也使用这种技巧，
where going to producer consumer style coordination between the hardware and software.
在硬件和软件之间进行生产者和消费者风格的协调。
So yeah, it's a very common structure.
所以，是的，它是非常常见的结构。
Maybe one or two questions, you can ask about it,
也许你可以问一两个问题，
like why is there actually even a queue, why is there a ring.
比如为什么是队列，为什么是环。
Okay, the reason there's a ring correct,
好的，这里有一个环，
because the queue wraps around, queue wraps around to make it fix size,
因为队列环绕使其大小固定，
but you know, why, why not, you know have queue one entry, one entry,
但是为什么不让队列一个条目，
like it's almost like the UART,
就像 UART 一样，
you remember the UART driver and controller
你还记得 UART 驱动程序和控制器
is basically only one register to send a byte
只有一个寄存器发送一个字节，
and there's another register receive a byte.
另一个寄存器接收一个字节。
And so why have, why go for this complicated scheme,
那么，为什么要选择这个复杂的方案，
you could have yourself a single register,
你可以只使用一个寄存器，
and then you can basically say you know hardware,
然后你可以告诉硬件，
this register is now ready, send it,
这个寄存器现在已经准备好了，发送它，
and then you just wait until the it's done.
然后你就等这件事完成。
To allow for when there are bursts of packets.
为了允许在有数据包突发时使用。
Yeah, yeah exactly,
是的，就是这样，
you know the network interface where the network card or cable is pretty high performance,
网卡或电缆的网络接口性能非常高，
in fact very high performance, gigabits per second.
性能非常高，每秒千兆。
And so, it can be hard for the core,
所以，这对核心来说可能很困难，
the processors actually keep up with it,
处理器跟上它，
so you would like to give it a whole bunch of packets,
所以你想给它一大堆数据包，
you know the networks or network card chunk along
网络或网卡[块]，
and all send them out at high speed.
把它们高速发送出去。
And similarly you know in reception you might get a burst of packets coming in
类似地，在接收中，你可能会收到突发的数据包进来，
and you want to place them in the queue
你想把它们放在队列里，
and then the operating system can start processing the queue, right.
然后操作系统开始处理队列。
And so this is a common,
所以这是一种常见的，
this is the reason, that these queues are common to handle bursts.
这就是原因，这些队列通常用于处理突发。
What happens if the queue is full, like reception.
如果队列满了怎么办，比如接收。
I think the the document mentioned that,
我想文件提到了，
it does some form of drop tail scheme.
它做了某种形式的丢弃尾的方案。
Yeah, there, yeah, basically the packets get dropped.
是的，基本上数据包会被丢弃。
So any future incoming packets,
所以，任何未来传入的数据包，
if the queue is full, the packets or there's no room anymore in the ring,
如果队列已满，环里没有地方了，
the network card can't do anything with that, correct,
网卡不能对它们执行任何操作，
and so the only option it actually has to basically delete the packet
所以它唯一能做的就是删除数据包，
or not added to the ring and therefore disappears.
或者没有添加到环中，因此消失。
So, one reason you know packet loss, sometimes is that,
所以，有时这是丢包的一个原因，
and operating system is overloaded,
并且操作系统过载，
you know with packet can't keep up and the ring fills
数据包跟不上，环被填满了，
and then you know the packets get dropped.
然后数据包会被丢弃。
You know higher level software,
更高级的软件，
of course maybe like TCP connection might re-transmit those packets,
比如 TCP 连接可能会重新传输这些数据包，
but this is one reason why packets can get dropped.
但这是数据包可能被丢弃的原因之一。
So even if the hardware sort of works all perfectly fine,
所以即使硬件运行得很好，
you know because of these bursts
由于这些突发，
you know it can happen that some packets might get dropped.
一些数据包可能会被删除。
So you had a really really big burst.
所以，你有一个非常大的突发。
The head and tail pointers,
头指针和尾指针，
they're all software abstractions, right, of the queue?
它们都是队列的软件抽象吧？
Okay, so these are actually turns out that
好的，这些是，
those are these control registers, right,
这些是控制寄存器，
so there's a control register for the hardware, the header pointer is,
所以有一个用于头指针的控制寄存器，
a control register for the basically the tail pointers,
有一个用于尾指针的控制寄存器，
there's no real distinction between hardware software,
硬件和软件之间没有真正的区分，
basically the driver knows about the tail pointer,
基本上驱动知道尾指针，
and it knows about the hardware knows about the tail pointer and header pointer
并且硬件知道尾指针和头指针，
and use a basic control registers.
并使用基本的控制寄存器。
Okay yeah.
好的，好的。
We will see the code in seconds,
我们稍后会看代码，
how did that shows up,
它是如何出现的，
make sure if you go back to our,
确保如果你回到，
maybe let's see this picture still here,
让我们看看这张图片还在这里，
here's that earlier picture we looked at,
这是我们之前看过的那张图片，
and you know here's control register that holds the head,
这是一个控制寄存器，持有头指针，
here's control register that holds the tail,
这是持有尾指针的控制寄存器，
and of course there's one for both reception and one for sending.
当然还有一个是接收的，一个是发送的。
Okay?
好的?
Let's go back here.
我们回到这里。
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about the descriptors.
好的，我们来谈谈描述符。
And so the descriptors are defined by the hardware
所以描述符由硬件定义的，
and so the hardware says
所以硬件表示，
like here's how the descriptors should look like,
这是描述符应该是什么样子，
and your driver you know these are the bits you can fill in,
而你的驱动，这些是可以填入的位，
and if you fill in that bit that tells me to follow, right.
如果你填入那个位，告诉我。
And so here's the two descriptors are important,
所以这里有两个描述符很重要，
you know, here's the receive descriptor rx,
这是接收描述符 rx ，
and here's a tx, one of the tx descriptors.
这是 tx 描述符。
And so let's look a little bit.
所以让我们稍微看一下。
Yeah, it's a little bit,
是的，它是，
probably the most important part is this address,
可能最重要的部分是这个地址，
and that is the address that the software filled in
这就是软件填写的地址，
to say where they should where the hardware to dump the packet,
说明硬件应该将数据包转存到哪里，
where in RAM to the driver,
在 RAM 的什么地方，
where should the network card put the data that is received into RAM,
网卡应该把接收到的数据放到 RAM 的什么地方，
so it's the address of the reception buffer, if you will.
所以，它是接收缓冲区的地址。
And then you know probably the most important part in
然后可能最重要的部分是
is the status field as you've seen.
是你已经看到的 status 字段。
So when the driver basically still continues to look sort of at the tail
所以当驱动还在继续查看尾指针的时候，
and sees that there's a new packet has been received
看到收到了一个新的数据包，
and the way it tells whether a new packet received is,
它判断是否接收到新数据包的方式是，
is that the DD bit, correct, is set by the hardware.
是 DD 位，是由硬件设置的。
And you know the shaded areas are the fields of the packet descriptor of the,
阴影区域是数据包描述符的字段，
receive descriptor actually the hardware fills in,
接收描述符是硬件填入的，
and the white you know the non shaded ones
白色的未加阴影的是
are the fields that actually shaded in are filled in by the software,
由软件填入的加阴影的字段，
again here we see this clear distinction about,
我们在这里看到了明显区别，
somethings are owned by software,
一些归软件所有，
somethings are owned by by the hardware.
一些归硬件所有。
Okay, and there's a similar you know descriptor,
好的，还有一个类似的描述符，
very simple descriptor that looks,
非常简单的描述符，
that's a hardware descriptor for the transmission,
是传输的硬件描述符，
it has an address,
它有一个地址，
the address of course is
这个地址当然是
the address where the data is in memory that needs to be sent.
需要发送的数据在内存中的地址。
And then it has a bunch of, has a command field,
然后它有一个 command 字段，
and here's how the software tells the driver tells the network card,
这是软件告诉驱动，告诉网卡，
this is what you should do with this particular packet
这是你应该对数据包执行的操作，
or you know this is what you should know about this particular packet.
或者这是你应该知道的关于这个数据包的信息。
And so one thing,
所以有一件事，
yeah we I think we [fill] in two packet, two things,
我想我们填入两个东西，
we call the EOP says you know the end of packet,
EOP 表示数据包的末尾，
and that basically tells the driver,
这告诉驱动程序，
this is the last descriptor of a particular packet,
这是数据包的最后一个描述符，
and now can you know send off you know whatever data that's in these descriptors.
现在，你可以发送这些描述符里的数据。
And I think we set the response you know requested command bit
我想我们设置了响应请求命令位，
or RS I think it is,
或者 RS ，
basically tells network card,
就是告诉网卡，
when you're done transmitting this thing,
当你完成传输这个东西，
you know set the, set the bit that it actually has been transmitted.
设置它实际传输的位。
We'll see in a second how how that shows up.
我们稍后会看到它是如何显示的。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
So one one thing to keep in mind,
所以有一件事要记住，
you know with these structures,
对于这些结构，
these are defined by the hardware,
这些都是由硬件定义的，
like hardware, software has no control over their structure,
软件不能控制它们的结构，
you know there's just literally defined by the hardware, by the network card.
这是由硬件和网卡定义的。
Okay, let's look at a little bit of code
好的，让我们看一小段代码，
and see what the solution looks like,
看看解决方案是什么样子，
and we'll look at a couple of issues
我们将看几个问题，
that we haven't looked at yet, you know the mbufs,
我们还没有看过的 mbuf ，
issues if during transmission and issues during receiving.
传输过程中的问题和接收过程中的问题。
And this would be presumably all well familiar with to you,
你们大概都很熟悉这一点，
given the fact that you just finished the lab.
考虑到你刚刚完成实验。
Okay, so here,
好的，那么这里，
just to go to the top, here's the transmit ring.
查看顶部，这是传送环。
Yeah, and that's basically the ring of descriptors,
是的，这就是描述符环，
you know we drew off in the last couple of slides.
我们在最后几张幻灯片中画到了。
There's a separate,
这里有一个单独的，
we talked briefly about this,
我们简要地谈过这个，
there's a separate basically ring of mbufs,
这里有一个独立的 mbuf 环，
but in that ring is completely you know a software or driver only abstraction,
但在这个环完全是软件或驱动程序抽象，
hardware, this is defined by this structure is defined by the hardware, right,
这个结构是硬件定义的，
and if you look at.
如果你看一下。
Oops.
哎呀。
You know look at the definitions,
查看定义，
but here's struct tx_desc,
这里是 tx_desc 结构体，
that corresponds to the C version of exactly the structure
这对应于 C 版本的结构体，
that actually was defined by the hardware,
由硬件定义的，
you know 64 bit address,
64 位地址，
you know the length field, the cso, byte the cmd byte,
length 字段， cso 字节， cmd 字节，
the status byte, the css byte, and then two word for special.
status 字节， css 字节，然后是 special 的两字节。
And there's a similar ring that is literally defined by the hardware,
还有一个类似的环，是由硬件定义的，
or similar descriptors received descriptor as defined by hardware,
或类似的接收描述符，是由硬件定义的，
and those we just have see descriptors corresponding to these hardware structures.
并且那些已经看到的描述符与这些硬件结构相对应。
Alright, let's look at transmit,
好的，让我们来看一下传输，
so here's the sort of staff solution for transmit,
这是一种用于传输的解决方案，
you know acquires a lock,
获取一把锁，
and the reason we said before that needed lock is,
我们之前说的需要锁的原因是，
because multiple functions or multiple threads, kernel threads
因为有多个函数或多个内核线程
might call transmit at the same time.
可能会同时调用 transmit 。
And then it looks at the tail,
然后它查看尾指针，
you know to see if there's any,
查看是否有，
in the room to actually sent a new packet,
在房间里发送新的数据包，
because you know the network card got behind,
因为网卡落后了，
and all the descriptors actually are be in used.
所有的描述符都在使用中。
And so the way it checks,
所以它检查的方式，
where you're actually the descriptor in the in use,
描述符是否在使用，
by checking whether the DD bit is not set.
通过检查是否未设置 DD 位。
And if it is set then,
如果它设置了，
if it's not set, then it returns immediately,
如果没有设置，则它立即返回，
not sending the packet at all,
根本不发送数据包，
and in any other case, gonna it keeps on,
在任何其他情况下，则继续下去，
going and actually will send the mbuf.
会发送 mbuf 。
So if there's still an mbuf in this position in the tx_mbufs,
所以，如果 tx_mbufs 中仍有 mbuf ，
and means this is an mbuf for a while back,
意味着这是[以前]的 mbuf ，
you know free that mbuf,
释放那个 mbuf ，
because we're going to actually stick in a new mbuf into this descriptor,
因为我们要把 mbuf 插入到这个描述符中，
we just need to remember,
我们只需要记住，
which you know mbuf we stuck in that descriptor,
我们插入哪个描述符，
and so the way we do that is
我们做到这一点的方法是
by keeping that in the tx_mbufs.
将其保存在 tx_mbuf 中。
And then we fill in the descriptor,
然后我们填入描述符，
and so the first thing we'll filling is the head
所以我们要填入的第一样东西是头指针，
and we fill in,
然后我们填入，
we put in the address the start of the first header in the mbuf,
我们把地址放入 mbuf 中第一个头指针的开始，
then, put the length, set the status 0,
然后，放入 length ， status 设置为 0 ，
put the command field in place
设置 cmd 字段，
by setting both RS and the EOP bit as we discuss the second.
通过设置 RS 和 EOP 位。
And, and then basically you'll be synchronized
然后，你会同步，
to make actually sure there's no reordering of,
以确保实际上没有重新排序，
you know that all these instructions are performed before the next instruction.
所有这些指令都是在下一条指令之前执行。
And what the next instruction does,
下一条指令所做的，
it actually updates the tail pointer,
它更新尾指针，
and so the [] updates the tail pointer,
所以，[]更新尾指针，
and the tail pointer correct is a control register in the network card,
尾指针是网卡中的一个控制寄存器，
and so basically when we update the tail pointer,
所以当我们更新尾部指针时，
the network card knows aha something changed,
网卡知道发生了变化，
and it's going to read you know the data at that descriptor,
它将读取那个描述符的数据，
and it's going to basically read these fields, we've just filled in,
它将读取我们刚刚填入的这些字段，
so we're gonna basically make absolutely sure that,
所以我们要绝对确保，
all these writes, all the stores are materialized in memory,
所有这些写入，所有的存储都在内存中实现，
before the network card actually reads them,
在网卡读取它们之前，
and so this is why the __sync_synchronize there,
这就是为什么那里有 __sync_synchronize 的原因，
and then we release about a lock,
然后我们释放锁，
and that's basically all we have to do to transmit a packet.
这就是我们传输数据包所要做的全部工作。
Can you explain the __sync_synchronize again, like what.
你能再解释一下 __sync_synchronize 吗，比如。
Yeah, it's mostly memory ordering technicality, correct,
是的，它是关于技术上的内存排序，
compilers are free to reorder instructions,
编译器可以自由地重新排序指令，
the writes might actually sit in the L1 cache or the L2 cache,
写入可能位于 L1 缓存或 L2 缓存中，
and sync basically the synchronize sort of memory fence,
基本上 synchronize 是内存屏障，
that tells the hardware and compiler,
告诉硬件和编译器，
please don't move any instructions across this barrier,
请不要通过屏障移动任何指令，
and make sure that all the data,
并确保所有数据，
that you know all the stores before this barrier
在这个屏障之前的所有保存，
are actually actually materialized in RAM.
都是在内存中实现的。
And the reason that is important is,
这很重要的原因是，
because the, go back to our picture for a little while ago,
因为，回到我们刚才的图片，
all the way back here.
一直回到这里。
Make sure both you know the RISC-V cores that run the driver code
确保运行驱动的 RISC-V 核心
basically put values here in round right,
将值放在这里，
but you know those values are [] the L1 cache and L2 cache
但这些值在 L1 缓存和 L2 缓存中，
and the memory flush and ensures that they actually show up in the RAM,
以及内存刷新，并确保它们出现在 RAM 中，
this is important because as soon as we update the tail pointer,
这一点很重要，因为只要我们更新尾指针，
the e1000 is going to look into RAM for these descriptors,
e1000 将在 RAM 中查找这些描述符，
and we've got to make sure that all the fields are indeed set,
我们必须确保所有的字段都设置好了，
otherwise, it would read stale values.
否则，它将读取过时的值。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Yep thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Why do mbuf exist,
为什么 mbuf 会存在，
why have these sort of separate structure of,
为什么会有这种分离的结构，
why have these two sort of corresponding structures?
为什么会有这两种对应的结构？
So I guess part of it is,
我想部分原因是，
it's all nice and well
这一切都很好，
if the driver needs to talk to the hardware about where things are,
如果驱动需要告诉硬件东西在哪里，
but at the end of the day,
但归根结底，
we do need to store the packet
我们确实需要保存数据包，
to hand off to the network stack somehow.
以便以某种方式将其传递到网络栈。
Yeah, exactly,
是的，就是这样，
you know, so you know so one way to think about it is
所以，考虑这个问题的一种方式是，
that the you know the mbufs completely an OS abstraction,
mbuf 完全是操作系统抽象，
nothing to do with really the network card at all,
与网卡一点关系都没有，
and it's there,
它之所以在那里，
because like you know if at some point, you know maybe receive a packet,
因为，如果在某个时候，可能会收到一个数据包，
you know we hand it off to the network stack,
我们把它送到网络栈，
in the network stack now sticks at some queue,
放到网络栈中的某个队列中，
so that when later a user process calls read,
这样当稍后用户进程调用 read 时，
you actually can read it,
你可以读它，
in the meantime, we need to have some structure,
同时，我们需要一些结构
that holds that data that we actually received
来保存我们收到的数据，
and that's exactly what those mbuf structures are.
这就是这些 mbuf 结构。
Sorry, can you talk about the,
抱歉，你能不能谈谈，
like how, how do you use the link list structure in your code,
比如，你如何在代码中使用链表结构，
because I was trying to to understand it and track it down
因为我试着去理解它并追踪它，
and it seems like there's some push tail or push head,
它似乎有一些 push tail 或 push head ，
but I don't ever call it in my code,
但我在我的代码里从来没有调用它，
oh, it might be it might be in the net.c file.
哦，它可能在 net.c 文件中。
The networks C files file, we gave you to, correct?
我们给你们的网络 C 文件吗？
Yeah.
是的。
And where you're thinking?
你想的是什么？
If you look for something like pull pop, I think pop.
如果你查找，比如 pull pop ，我想是 pop 。
Yeah, so this is this is the only place
是的，这是唯一的地方，
where it looks like it does things with the linked list structure of mbuf,
看起来使用了 mbuf 的链表结构，
and if you don't ever call this function or the push tail,
如果你不调用这个函数或 push tail ，
you basically just treat the mbuf as an array of like how many characters,
你只是将 mbuf 视为一个由多少个字符组成的数组，
so, so why is mbuf there.
那么，为什么 mbuf 会在那里。
Because here, when you receive a UDP packet,
因为在这里，当你收到 UDP 数据包时，
so the UDP packet comes in from the network card,
因此 UDP 数据包从网卡传入，
it goes to the network stack,
它进入网络栈，
then the UDP packet,
然后是 UDP 数据包，
the mbuf for the UDP that holds that UDP packet
UDP 的 mbuf 持有 UDP 数据包，
is actually stuck in a queue right here,
在这个队列中，
on the socket for the receiver.
在接收者的插槽上。
And so this is the reason that you can have queues within mbufs.
这就是为什么你有 mbuf 队列的原因。
And the reason is stack in the queue there correct,
原因是栈在队列中，
is because you know who knows,
是因为你知道，
you know the user process that's going to read you know from this particular socket,
用户进程要从这个套接字读取，
you know might be doing something else,
也可能在做别的事，
and at some point later, it's going to call the read system call,
在随后的某个时刻，它调用 read 系统调用，
then the read system call is going to move you know that mbuf from that socket.
然后 read 系统调用将从那个套接字中移动 mbuf 。
And so, the point with each socket can have a list of mbufs for reception.
所以，每个套接字可以具有用于接收的 mbuf 列表。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, let's go back to the driver.
好的，让我们回到驱动上。
So that was transmit.
所以那是传输。
So then we receive,
然后我们接收，
you know almost similar, not that much difference,
几乎是一样的，没有太大差别，
basically you know read the tail pointer from the network card.
基本上从网卡读取尾指针。
You see there actually a packet,
你可以看到那里有一个数据包，
and if there's a packet, then the DD field would be set,
如果有数据包，则 DD 字段会被设置，
if the DD field is not set,
如果 DD 字段没有设置，
then we know there's no packet and so we're done,
然后我们知道没有数据包，我们就结束了，
if it is set, we're going to read it,
如果设置了，我们就去读它，
and read the length,
读取长度，
you know, and when we when we call and net_rx,
当我们调用 net_rx 时，当我们调用和net_rx时，
you know do up call into the higher level stack.
向上调用更高级别的栈。
And when we're done,
当我们完成时，
you know we're basically free up you know that entry,
我们会释放那个条目，
so that the driver can use it
以便驱动程序可以使用它
to actually receive more packets in it.
来接收更多数据包。
And the real crucial operation there is, correct,
真正的关键的操作是，
we bump up basically the tail to tell the driver,
我们撞上尾指针告诉驱动程序，
okay, you know we're done with it, you can use it again,
我们已经用完了，你可以再次使用，
you know here's again that slot.
这里的那个位置。
So maybe the most interesting question is
所以也许最有趣的问题是
and number of questions have you asked,
你们问的很多问题，
why is the while there,
为什么这里有一个 while ，
why is this in a loop,
为什么这是一个循环，
don't you get an interrupt,
不是你获得中断，
then you know you grab one packet then you've done,
你抓到一个数据包，然后你就完成了，
a number of people that actually forgot while loop first,
很多人首先忘记了 while 循环，
you know notice that basically at some point
注意，在某个时刻，
you don't receive packets anymore, during nettest.
在 nettest 中，你不能接收到数据包。
Is it because you would like to transmit as many packets
是因为你希望传输尽可能多的包，
that are ready as possible with only one interrupt,
仅使用一个中断，
so that you can kind of amortize the cost of the interrupt.
这样你就可以在摊销中断的成本。
Yeah, this, this is absolutely part of it,
是的，这绝对是其中的一部分，
you know you get to the,
你获得，
let's first talk about you know the root cause is write,
我们先来谈谈，根本原因是写入，
if a number of burst package comes in,
如果一些突发包进来了，
and the network card will generate the interrupt,
网卡将产生中断，
but more packets are coming in,
但是有更多的包进来了，
and so it will just put them in the free descriptors right
所以它会把它们放在空闲描述符中，
that actually can use,
可以使用的，
can't generate more interrupts,
无法生成更多中断，
because already generated interrupt,
因为已经生成中断，
and at some point you know the whatever the process
在某种程度上，不管是什么进程，
or you know, maybe we were the core was just in a section of code that turned off interrupts,
或者核心在一段关闭中断的代码中，
because it was doing something atomic,
因为它在做一些原子性的事情，
at the end of it,
在它的最后，
you know there's a release from lock,
有一个锁的释放，
that actually turns interruption on,
它打开了中断，
that point of time,
那个时间点，
then basically the receive handlers, the interrupt handler going to run,
然后接收中断处理程序继续运行，
but between a period,
但是在一段时间内，
when the first packet comes in and before you receive handler runs,
当第一个包传入到接收处理程序运行之前，
there's a whole bunch of other packets might have could have could have come in.
可能还有一大堆其他的包进来了。
And so we don't run in the while loop,
所以我们不在 while 循环中运行，
will leave those packets,
会留下这些数据包，
will grab the first one and will grab the other
会抓到第一个，也会抓到另一个，
and the later ones you stick there in the queue, right,
后面的放在队列里，
they're just sitting there in that ring.
它们就在那个环里。
Now, if subsequent interrupt would come in,
现在，如果随后的中断进来，
we'll grab the next one,
我们会抓取下一个，
but like the tests,
但就像测试一样，
you know what they do they run their UDP packets,
他们所做的，他们会运行 UDP 数据包，
you know, so they send off a whole bunch,
他们会发送一大堆，
like one of the test since like ten ping request in parallel,
比如，一个测试是并行发送 10 个 ping 请求，
you know the ten responses coming parallel back, you know correct.
有 10 个回复也是并行的。
The first one receives generates an interrupt,
第一个接收到的产生中断，
the other nine go into the queue,
其他九个进入队列，
the higher level software, you know reached the first one,
更高级的软件到达第一个，
and then returns like it's done,
然后完成并返回，
and at that point, nothing happens anymore,
在这一点上，什么都不会发生，
because the receiver is waiting for more receive packets,
因为接收者正在等待更多的接收数据包，
they happen to be there,
它们碰巧在那里，
they're sitting in the ring,
它们在环中，
except you know the receive didn't do them in a while loop
除了接收不是在 while 循环中做的，
and so didn't pick them up.
所以没有去取出它们。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So, for example if the test programs would have sent,
所以，比如，如果测试程序会发送，
one request waited for a response,
一个请求等待响应，
then you would never notice that, you needed to a while loop.
你永远不会注意到，需要一个 while 循环。
And it's because like there's a burst of responses might come back,
因为会有突发的回复回来，
and that only generate together one interrupt.
而这只会一起产生一个中断。
Any questions about that, about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
I have a question,
我有个问题，
so for example if instead of a while one,
比如，除了 while(1) ，
we would have a for loop that just goes through the whole queue,
我们有一个遍历整个队列的 for 循环，
that would also be wrong for the same reason.
出于同样的原因，这也是错误的。
No, we skip all the ones that have the DD not set.
不，我们跳过所有未设置 DD 的列表。
Okay, we should only we should only look at packets
好的，我们应该只看数据包，
and actually we should only look at the tail pointer.
我们应该只看尾指针。
But you know in principle, you could just skip the whole queue
但是原则上，你可以跳过整个队列，
and I guess look at the DD packets,
我想查看 DD 数据包，
you know let them see the DD bit is set,
让它们看到 DD 位已设置，
and that might work, I don't know I haven't tried that.
这可能行得通，我还没试过。
Okay, but isn't the device able to
好的，但是是不是设备可以
put more mbufs in the receive after we read stale?
在我们读到旧数据之后，在接收器里放更多的 mbuf ？
Yeah yeah.
是的，对。
Okay.
好的。
And we have to.
我们必须。
It's very dangerous,
这是非常危险的，
like this proposal of like sort of looking around,
这个提议是查看，
and you know seeing DD set,
查着 DD 设置，
because you know really we should do,
因为我们应该这么做，
we should not look at buf that really are controlled by the driver or by the hardware,
我们不应该查看由驱动程序或硬件控制的 buf ，
and only look at buffers are actually available to the software
只需查看软件可用的缓冲区，
and which is indicated by the DD bit,
是由 DD 位表示的，
and basically by looking at the tail pointer.
通过查看尾指针。
Basically, anything owned between the tail and the head is owned by the hardware.
基本上，尾部和头部之间的任何东西都归硬件所有。
Going back to the mbuf, like the reason we need the mbuf,
回到 mbuf ，就像我们需要 mbuf 的原因，
why do we need the other information in the buffer like the [] array,
为什么我们需要缓冲区中的其他信息，比如[]数组，
I think it's called the backing store.
我想它叫做[后备存储]。
It gets in net.h.
它在 net.h 中。
So we need we need the buf field, correct,
所以我们需要 buf 字段，
because it actually contains the data.
因为它包含了数据。
I thought the head contains a pointer to the data.
我认为头部包含指向数据的指针。
Yeah yeah okay,
好的，好的，
but the buf actually is the actual allocates space,
但是 buf 是实际分配的空间，
you know the whole packets, right,
这个数据包，
and then head get pointers into buf,
然后头部使用指针进入 buf ，
basically the start of the packet.
是数据包的开头。
Okay, okay.
好的，好的。
And this is mbuf, this is,
这是 mbuf ，这是，
okay so a little bit more context to mbuf is
好的， mbuf 的更多上下文是
a structure that you see in a lot of network stacks,
你在许多网络栈中看到的结构，
so you look in the Linux kernel,
所以你看一下 Linux 内核，
you'll see structure similar like this,
你会看到类似这样的结构，
and it's typically called mbufs, and so we have to.
它通常被称为 mbufs ，所以我们必须。
We could have simplified this structure quite a bit, if we wanted to
我们可以把这个结构简化很多，
and maybe subsequent here is we should,
或许接下来我们应该，
but this is sort of the standard way
但这是一种标准方法，
in which packets are represented in operating system kernels.
数据包在操作系统内核中的表示。
Okay, any further questions about this?
好的，关于这个，还有什么问题吗？
So I have a choice now,
所以我现在有一个选择，
a couple of things I could say about the network driver,
关于网络驱动程序，我可以说几件事，
but then I won't have any time to talk about mmap.
但是那样我就没有时间谈论 mmap 了。
I could also talk a little bit about mmap and then and stop here,
我也可以稍微谈一下 mmap ，然后到此为止，
in terms of talking to the network driver.
而不是讨论网络驱动程序。
Any preferences?
有什么偏好吗？
No preferences.
没有偏好。
Let me talk a little bit about mmap,
让我简单介绍一下 mmap ，
because there was a question that came up a couple times,
因为有几次出现了一个问题，
and that might be worth addressing,
这可能是值得解决的问题，
it's almost more a question about you know why mmap exists,
这几乎更多的是关于 mmap 为什么存在的问题，
then, you know actually how to implement it.
然后，是如何实现它。
So there's no real objections which sounds different,
所以没有听起来不同的反对意见，
let me talk a little bit more about mmap.
让我更多地谈谈 mmap 。
So this is your last chance
所以，这是最后的机会，
to ask any questions about the network driver until the end of class.
询问有关网络驱动程序的问题，在下课之前。
Okay, let's talk about the mbufs, oh, mmap.
好的，我们来谈谈 mbufs ，哦， mmap 。
Okay, so the, the question really relates to sort of the file system API,
好的，这个问题与文件系统 API 有关，
and so the file system has a reasonable broad API,
文件系统具有相当广泛的 API ，
supporting directories, symbolic links, hard links, etc etc,
支持目录，符号链接，硬链接等，
but presumably the main the main part of it is the the file API, correct,
但是它的主要部分是文件 API ，
the file API, you're well familiar to you now,
文件 API ，你现在已经很熟悉了，
open the file, you know with some permissions,
打开文件，有一些权限，
and once you have opened the file,
一旦你打开了文件，
you know you can read from the file,
你可以从文件中读取，
into a buffer, create some data.
读到缓冲区中，创建一些数据。
And you can write you know to the file,
你写入到文件，
whatever file descriptor and buf, you know len,
不管是文件描述符和 buf 还是 len ，
so let's say we,
假设我们，
and then we can close the file descriptor.
然后我们可以关闭文件描述符。
Now let's say we want to write an application
现在假设我们想要编写一个应用程序，
and you can think about the,
你可以想一想，
you know may be just a file as, you know files normally a array of bytes,
可能只是一个文件，有普通的字节数组，
but like maybe this application has sort of
但是这个应用程序可能有
it's an array of struct that are stored in it.
它是一个结构数组保存在其中。
So, and let's say the application wants to update the struct,
所以，假设应用程序想要更新结构，
so you know we have to file,
我们必须操作文件，
here's a file and so divided in you know structs,
这是一个文件，分成结构体，
you know whatever zero to use the file length,
从 0 到文件长度，
and you know we maybe like in the middle,
我们可能在中间，
let's have structure 16 bytes or something
让我们有一个 16 字节的结构，或别的什么，
and you know we want to update one of these
我们想要更新其中的一个，
or maybe want to update the first one.
或者可能想要更新第一个。
And so in a way we could do that correctly,
所以，我们可以做到这一点，
we read and we open the file,
我们读，我们打开文件，
we read you know the first you know whatever 16 bytes,
我们读开始的 16 个字节，
that correspond to this you know we,
对应于这个，
let's say updates you know the first field struct,
假设更新第一个字段结构，
the first byte of that struct, you know to be 1.
那个结构的第一个字节，改为 1 。
And then we call write, to basically write it back
然后我们调用 write ，将其写回，
and then we close the file.
然后我们关闭文件。
So if when is write happens where,
那么，如果写入发生在那里，
where does it actually write.
它实际写入的位置是哪里。
So we've set this memory above the 1,
所以我们把内存改为 1 ，
you know will this first by change to 1,
这个会不会先变成 1 ，
if we call write.
如果我们调用 write 。
So, remember the file descriptor has not set associated with it correct.
请记住，文件描述符没有设置与它关联。
And reads read pushes that offset you know forward,
然后读取将偏移量向前推，
in this case, we've read 16 bytes,
在这个例子中，我们读取 16 个字节，
you know the offset goes from up 0 to 16.
偏移量从 0 上升到 16 。
And so where does write write,
那么 write 在哪里写呢，
as you notice, there's no offset argument in the write system call,
正如你注意到的，在 write 系统调用中没有偏移量参数，
so where does it write.
那么它写在哪里。
Len?
长度？
Yeah you we'll write len bytes,
是的，我们将写入 len 字节，
which offset in the file,
在文件中的哪个偏移量，
presumably len exactly at 16 right.
假设 len 对应 16 。
Yes.
是的。
Write here, so which, this byte will change to 1, correct.
那么这个字节会变成 1 。
Not the actual thing that we are actually trying to modify.
而不是我们实际想要修改的东西。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So the way you've written this application,
所以你写这个应用的方式，
it turns out there was one a system call,
有一次系统调用，
that we didn't really talk much about at all,
我们并没有太多谈论，
but every operating system, Unix operating system is called system called lseek.
但是每一种 Unix 操作系统都被称为 lseek 。
And lseek allows you basically to change the offset to some position.
lseek 允许你将偏移量更改为某个位置。
And so in this particular case,
所以在这个案例中，
we want to do have the effect
我们想要的效果是，
that we're going to write this struct not that one.
我们要写这个结构，而不是那个。
Then we would have said like you know lseek 0,
那么我们就会说 lseek 0 ，
basically resetting the offset to actually 0,
将偏移量重置为 0 ，
so then this write would actually sort here now offset 0.
然后这个写操作是偏移量 0 。
And then this write actually you would write actually at the first 16 bytes.
然后这个 write 写入前 16 个字节。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So this is slightly inconvenient, correctly,
所以这有点不方便，
if you think about this,
如果你仔细想想，
you look at this interface,
你看这个接口，
there's actually quite a bit of stuff going on,
有相当多的东西在运行，
you know you gotta open, you gotta read it,
你需要打开，需要读取，
you know you can seek it and then you can write it.
你需要查找，然后可以写入。
And so, one reason that mmap is popular,
所以， mmap 流行的原因之一，
is you can sort of avoid you know these these complications.
是你可以避免这些复杂的情况。
Because if we write this using mmap,
因为如果我们用 mmap 写这个，
you know, we do fd is open
我们做的打开 fd ，
and we open the file as before,
我们像以前一样打开文件，
and then you know we just call mmap,
然后我们只需要调用 mmap ，
it's going to be whatever our struct,
不管我们的结构是什么，
let's say our struct h, you know, blah, blah blah,
比如我们的结构体 h ，等等，
you know whatever some len for the file, read, write permissions,
文件的长度，读、写权限，
you know map shared, and file descriptor 0.
映射共享，文件描述符为 0 。
And then, so now basically with this correct we're in mmapping,
然后，我们就在 mmap 中了，
you know the file f at the location h, you know in memory.
文件 f 在 h 位置在内存中。
Now, we can just say h
现在，我们可以说 h ，
whatever first byte is zero or one that we did before.
不管第一个字节是 0 还是 1 ，就像我们之前做的那样。
And then you know at some point you know we can munmap,
然后，在某个时刻，我们可以调用 munmap ，
you know the munmap h, right,
munmap h ，
and so if we think about this, we look in memory.
如果我们思考这个问题，我们在内存中查找。
We're looking at this from the perspective of the file,
我们是从文件的角度来看这件事，
you know what this does, correct,
这能解决的问题，
code literally did is basically you've got a pointer to this h,
代码说做的，你获得一个指向 h 的指针，
and you can just update here, you know that thing to 1
你可以更新这个东西为 1 ，
and be done with it, right.
然后就完成了。
And so if we sort of need to manipulate
所以，如果我们需要操作
you know file structure, data structure that sits inside of a file,
文件结构，位于文件中的数据结构，
this mmap interface is much more convenient.
这 个mmap 接口要方便得多。
Then you know this previous interface,
然后之前的接口，
we're you know we have to read,
我们必须读取，
you know we manipulated the memory you know we you know we seek back,
我们操纵内存，我们找回，
and then we actually write the information.
然后我们写下信息。
And in this particular case,
在这个案例中，
we really can think about the file as being an array of bytes,
我们可以将文件看作是字节数组，
you know that we can write willy nilly,
我们可以随意书写，
without actually having to navigate to jump around,
而不必[导航]来跳来跳去，
do people see what the advantage of the mmap interfaces.
人们看到 mmap 接口的优势了吗。
Any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
Any big storage systems use this,
有没有大型存储系统都使用这种方式，
like I don't know like databases,
比如数据库，
do they use this a lot or not really.
它们是经常使用还是不经常使用。
They use this a lot.
它们经常用这个。
I think a lot of applications use mmap,
我认为很多应用程序都使用 mmap ，
because for these kinds of things like a database is much more convenient,
因为对于像数据库这样的东西来说要方便得多，
then this interface, this interface is great, correct,
这个接口非常好，
if you need to read from standard input,
如果你需要从标准输入读取，
and there's a stream of bytes coming in,
有一个字节流进入，
you read you read you read and you produce some output some other stream.
你读取，并产生一些其他的输出流。
That interface that interface is very suitable for here,
那个接口非常适合，
you don't have to update offset,
你不必更新偏移量，
you know you read, get offset immediately update,
你读取，立即更新偏移量，
you read again, you read a bit further etc etc.
你再次读取，等等。
So it's really good for stream oriented input.
所以它对于面向流的输入来说很好。
Well, this is really good,
嗯，这真的很不错，
you know if the file has data structure,
如果文件有数据结构，
and use one of sort of update basic pieces of the file,
并且更新文件的部分，
and you know arbitrary locations.
任意的位置。
Okay, let's see,
好的，让我想想，
I'm going to start on about to run out of time.
我的时间快用完了。
So let me so stop here,
所以让我停在这里，
hopefully this one tidbit about mmap,
希望这个关于 mmap 的小道消息，
you know it's useful to know,
知道这一点很有用，
and tells you why you know that sort of is a popular scheme.
告诉你为什么这是一个很受欢迎的方案。
Let's see,
让我们看看,
so I I think that actually you know we were basically we come to the end of this lecture
我想，我们这节课快结束了，
and I guess the end of the end of six the six 6.S081,
也是 6.S081 的结束，
and so again you know if you have not filled out the feedback survey,
所以，如果你没有填写反馈调查，
you know please do so,
请这样做，
you know we appreciate if you fill out the subject evaluation.
如果你能填一下科目评估，我们会很感激的。
And and again I wanna thank you for your attention,
我再一次感谢你们的关注，
again it is a strange semester,
这又是一个奇怪的学期，
I wish I could have met you all in person.
我希望我能见到你们所有人。
Talk to you in person either class or before class or after class,
无论是上课还是课前或课后都可以和你面谈，
and unfortunately, as it happened,
不幸的是，正如它所发生的，
but I hope you got quite a bit of 6.S081
但我希望你能从 6.S081 学到很多，
and certainly with the staff and thank you for the engagement,
当然还有工作人员，感谢你们的努力，
you guys have been wonderful this semester.
这学期你们都表现得很棒。
So with that, thank you.
到此为止，谢谢。
If you have any questions, please hang around.
如果你有任何问题，请不要离开。
But I'm sure some of you have deadlines.
但我相信，你们中的一些人有最后期限。
Honestly on behalf of the TAs as well,
老实说，我也代表助教，
we've really enjoyed all the time
我们真的很享受这些时间，
we spent with you guys in office hours and doing check offs,
跟你们在上班时间以及做检查，
and this is the first semester, we've done check offs,
这是我们做检查的第一学期，
and then David and I both found it a really enjoyable process,
然后 David 和我都觉得这是一个非常愉快的过程，
and you know hopefully we were able to
希望我们能够
help you guys out and have some good conversations as well,
帮你们摆脱困境，并进行一些愉快的交谈，
so thanks for making it a great semester
所以，感谢你们让这学期过得很棒，
and adjusting on the fly with us
和我们一起在线上，
with all of the remote learning problems,
解决所有的远程学习问题，
we've run into and had to deal with
我们遇到并解决，
an absolute pleasure achieving this course.
完成这一课程的乐趣。
Any further questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Again, feel free to hang around.
再说一次，你可以随便提问。
Oh, I had a question,
哦，我有个问题，
so, it's it's oh yeah,
所以，哦，是的，
thank you so much for the class,
非常感谢你的课程，
I really like class, the best class semester,
我真的很喜欢这门课，这是最好的一学期，
I wanted to ask about the interrupts, the received interrupts,
我想问一下中断，接收的中断，
how does the how does the hardware knows when when the software has finished,
硬件如何知道软件何时完成，
handling the previous interrupt, not issue another one.
处理上一个中断，而不是发出另一个中断。
Because the there's multiple steps,
因为有多个步骤，
one is you know you're looking e1000 at the bottom,
一是你看到 e1000 的下半部分，
we re-enable interrupts
我们重新启用中断，
or we tell the card,
或者我们告诉网卡，
we're ready to receive further interrupts.
我们已经准备好接收更多中断。
So that's why we tell the card to generate interrupts,
这就是我们告诉网卡产生中断，
of course at this point interrupts actually not really turned on,
当然，在这一点上，中断并没有打开，
and we just tells the card you can generate interrupts again,
我们只需告诉网卡，你可以再次生成中断，
the interrupts get turned on, correct,
中断被打开，
like you know by you know these functions, you know interrupt enable
正如这些函数，中断启用，
and at that point, if you turn on interrupt enable,
在这一点上，如果你打开中断启用，
if this field set, plus you know the point where you turn on interrupt enable
如果设置了此字段，再加上启用中断，
and actually interrupt might happen again.
中断可能会再次发生。
Right, I forgot about this register, thank you so much.
好的，我忘了这个寄存器，非常感谢。
Yeah, it's just like one instruction, easy to miss.
是的，就像一条指令，很容易漏掉。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Thank you all.
谢谢大家。
Thank you, okay.
谢谢你，好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢。